<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-5B9F25B5-5FE1-4E38-BC8D-A0273F458C36" xml:lang="en"><title>Discreet
pop-up</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Discreet pop-up component displays notifications without blocking ongoing
task flows in the UI. When discreet pop-up is displayed, the background is
not dimmed and the user can continue interacting with the underlying application
normally. Discreet pop-up can contain an icon and a maximum of two rows of
text. Pop-up can have simple touch interaction, for example, tapping the pop-up
can open the application. </p>
<p>Discreet pop-up can be used to replace following note types:<ul>
<li><p>Error note</p></li>
<li><p>Warning note</p></li>
<li><p>Information note</p></li>
<li><p>Confirmation note</p></li>
</ul>Discreet pop-up does not replace wait notes, progress notes or the soft
notifications in the home screen. Application can have soft notification on
the home screen and use discreet pop-up to display information of the events
in other parts of the UI.</p>
<p>Discreet pop-ups can be displayed in touch and non-touch devices. For non-touch
devices, the touch functionality of the component is disabled.</p>
<fig id="GUID-B96EA28D-1BA7-4082-89C5-FD5E4549B0DB">
<title>Discreet pop-up</title>
<image href="GUID-EDC39EFF-B633-41DE-93A4-A52D2E7A4A64_d0e90175_href.jpg" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>Based on the purpose of use, there are two types of discreet pop-ups:<ul>
<li><p><b>Global discreet pop-ups</b> - displayed irrespective of the active
application (always displayed on the top of any active application). </p></li>
<li><p><b>Local discreet pop-ups</b> - displayed only if the application displaying
the note is on the foreground. </p></li>
</ul></p>
<note> New discreet pop-up always overrides old one except local pop-up can
never override global pop-up.</note>
<table id="GUID-D0E86336-C66C-4833-9E2B-55579889C914"><title>Default touch
events in Discreet pop-up.</title>
<tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.90*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.97*"/><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.15*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry valign="top"><p>User action</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>State change</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>Tactile feedback</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release on discreet pop-up</p></entry>
<entry><p>Performs the pop-up specific action, if any is defined. Else, pop-up
is dismissed.</p></entry>
<entry><p>If tap performs an action, then basic list effect and audio feedback
is provided with touch down and basic list effect on release events. If pop-up
is dismissed, then touch down provides pop-up effect.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release outside Discreet pop-up area</p></entry>
<entry><p>Application-specific. No effect on pop-up</p></entry>
<entry><p>Context specific</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and hold on discreet pop-up</p></entry>
<entry><p>Pop-up is displayed on the screen until the user releases the finger
and the pop-up specific action is performed, or pop-up is dismissed if no
action defined. In case pop-up is replaced with another discreet pop-up while
touch down action, touch release has no effect.</p></entry>
<entry><p><ul>
<li><p>Basic list effect and audio feedback is provided with touch down event.</p></li>
<li><p>If touch release performs an action, then basic list effect is provided
with it. If it closes the pop-up, then pop-up effect is provided.</p></li>
<li><p>If there is no action defined for touch release, then no tactile feedback
on touch release is provided.</p></li>
</ul> </p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<section id="GUID-1019914A-731E-4185-9D83-E9DF34976257"><title>Using discreet
pop-ups in applications</title>The API to use for the discreet pop-up is the
Discreet Pop-up API. </section>
<section id="GUID-17690B13-0C47-49E3-893C-98B371AD5230">To use a discreet
pop-up in the application, an instance of <xref href="GUID-4C38C9A4-6518-3994-AE3B-CBE49C22B337.dita"><apiname>CAknDiscreetPopup</apiname></xref> need
not be created; only a static call is required to display the pop-up. The
UI framework handles the creation and destruction of <xref href="GUID-4C38C9A4-6518-3994-AE3B-CBE49C22B337.dita"><apiname>CAknDiscreetPopup</apiname></xref> instances. </section>
</conbody></concept>