<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
	Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->  <!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd"><concept id="GUID-DAF35D49-9630-4186-A350-E8483693D50D" xml:lang="en"><title>Hierarchical
column list</title><prolog><metadata><keywords></keywords></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Hierarchical column list is used for browsing in one view files and folders
that are in different levels in the file system. This enables for example
showing subtitles among the list items, and collapsing and expanding data
items under it.</p>
<fig id="GUID-0A22D779-41C5-41DD-884C-AFC7DF192720">
<title>Hierarchical column list component, where the subtitle "Yesterday"
is expanded</title>
<image href="GUID-573420CD-E8E0-4E98-B3E2-1388F4B1137D_d0e80779_href.png" scale="40" placement="inline"></image>
</fig>
<p>The hierarchical column list can have three different row types:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Subtitle row </p></li>
<li><p>Core data row </p></li>
<li><p>Simple data row</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Subtitle can have only one type of subitems, thus both core data and simple
data items cannot exist under same subtitle. It is recommended, that only
one type of subitems would be used in the same view.</p>
<p>To enable more information in a single row, the core data row can be divided
into two core data columns. The more important information should be shown
in the first column due to more space, for example e-mail sender information
in the first column, and subject in the second column. In landscape there
can be also third column in use.</p>
<p><b>General navigation:</b> </p>
<p>Expanding and collapsing can be done in subtitle rows:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Arrow key: Tabs can be used together with a hierarchical column list,
and thus arrow keys are used for moving between tabs. If there are no tabs,
the arrow keys expand subtitle item (Arrow right, the focus is not moved)
and collapse expanded subtitle item (Arrow left, focus is not moved). </p></li>
<li><p>The Selection key expands collapsed (or vice versa) subtitle item in
focus. </p></li>
<li><p>Commands for expanding, collapsing and opening folders or files are
also available in the <b>Options</b> menu.</p></li>
</ul>
<section><title>Using hierarchical column
lists in C++ applications</title><p>The API to use for hierarchical column
lists is the Hierarchical
lists API. For implementation information, see Using
the Hierarchical lists API.</p></section>
</conbody></concept>