<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-29B84A67-9DB7-5F4C-A4D1-A3BDC69015A8" xml:lang="en"><title>Additional
System Wide Power States</title><shortdesc>A base port can add new power states to improve power management
for phone hardware. </shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>The Kernel defines three system wide power states. A base port can add
new power states to improve power management for phone hardware. </p>
<p>The generic system wide power states that are defined are <i>Active</i>, <i>Standby</i> and <i>Off</i>.
Any additional sub-states of the <i>Active</i> power state must be wholly
managed by the base port. These states may not need to be declared explicitly
and may result from peripherals, or groups of peripherals, having moved to
their low power state (see also <xref href="GUID-1D3E61BD-C09D-51FD-A10B-22392FDAEFEC.dita#GUID-1D3E61BD-C09D-51FD-A10B-22392FDAEFEC/GUID-DCB8EA90-9B5F-5BA1-8D22-124980AC6B34">moving
to their low power state</xref>). The device will then “trickle“ into one
of these sub-states instead of transitioning into them as a result of a user
action or system policy decision. </p>
<p>Usually, the transition of the system into one of the additional low power
states happens when the CPU enters the idle mode. The transition may be automatic
and wholly managed by the ASSP hardware or may result from an action taken
by the software routine that prepares the CPU to go to idle mode. </p>
<section id="GUID-22A20CBB-6BF2-495F-B32C-63834DD4624C"><title>Sleeping in idle mode</title> <p>An example of this is when
the base port uses the idle mode to put the CPU and the device into hardware
“Sleep” mode similar to that which can be achieved with a transition to <i>Standby</i> mode
as described in the implementation issues for <xref href="GUID-34D1D0BF-20DE-5677-A067-8FF9DD72E703.dita#GUID-34D1D0BF-20DE-5677-A067-8FF9DD72E703/GUID-1F77C71C-D226-58BB-ABAE-43F958CC0C61">implementing
DPowerController::PowerDown()</xref>  </p> <p>When called, the power controller’s <xref href="GUID-34D1D0BF-20DE-5677-A067-8FF9DD72E703.dita#GUID-34D1D0BF-20DE-5677-A067-8FF9DD72E703/GUID-E2A072D0-A67F-5E6D-81ED-CFD77B6ED4F1">DPowerController::CpuIdle() </xref> implementation
could take the necessary steps to prepare the CPU and the platform to go to
“Sleep”. </p> <p>There is a balance between the power savings obtained from
moving the CPU and platform into “Sleep” mode in Idle and the performance
hit resulting from spending time restoring the status after coming out of
“Sleep” mode. Usually the <codeph>CpuIdle()</codeph> routine investigates
the timer queue (using <xref href="GUID-C54D99AA-FF6E-3023-8260-8F5A88FBFBE0.dita#GUID-C54D99AA-FF6E-3023-8260-8F5A88FBFBE0/GUID-69103F26-2C21-3ECA-9DB5-C31A41F6C238"><apiname>NTimerQ::IdleTime()</apiname></xref>) for the next
timer expiration and decides to move or not to move the CPU and platform into
“Sleep” mode based on how much time there is before the next timer expiration.
The threshold above which it is considered productive to move into “Sleep”
is dependent on the base port. </p> <p>The decision to move into “Sleep” mode
may also be based on the current level of activity, or collected metrics on
the length of time spent in Idle, or other historical information. This can
be implemented entirely by the base port, or it may require the services of
an external component (such as, for example, Speed Management). </p> <p>The
transition to a hardware “Sleep” mode may also depend on shared peripherals
being in a particular state, for example, no pending requests from other peripherals.
This means that the power controller may need to check with the peripheral
driver before initiating the change. The power controller could use the ASSP/Variant
method to access the resource manager and check the usage of a shared peripheral
using its <codeph>GetCount()</codeph> API. </p> <p>The decision to move into
“Sleep” mode could be dependent on a number of peripherals (shared and not
shared) being in Standby and a number of controllable power resources being
turned off. Therefore the power controller may also need to check with the
resource manager (through the Variant or ASSP) for the state of a specific
set of controllable power resources (using the <codeph>ResourceManager::GetResourceState()</codeph> API). </p> <p>On
going to “Sleep”, an action or set of actions might need to be taken that
would affect the whole platform. An example of this is when DRAM is put into
self-refresh mode on entering the CPU Idle mode after all peripherals that
might access it (including the LCD controller and DSP) are in low power state.
Unused DRAM banks may also be powered down. </p> <p>The following diagram
exemplifies how the evolution of system power would look like on a system
when the most power saving “Sleep” mode can only be reached – from Idle -
when Peripherals A, B and C are already in their low power mode. On going
to the most power saving “Sleep” mode, additional actions can be taken to
lower the system power level: </p> <fig id="GUID-05ED7A51-E1A1-5D2E-AF81-A11A9EC80D7F">
<title>System power use over time</title>
<image href="GUID-BF157EE2-B680-554A-AE32-69C652B61FA6_d0e401620_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> <ul>
<li id="GUID-FD4E14B6-9471-5A91-B215-E42595645A94"><p>The system is active
when a request for service is made on peripheral A; the peripheral driver
for peripheral A requests its transition to operational state increasing the
system power requirement (a). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-FB7914E6-13BC-57C7-BA02-A7DAA3A4F968"><p>After a period of activity
related to servicing the request, the system enters the idle thread; in <codeph>CpuIdle()</codeph> the
time for the next timer expiration is investigated and is found to be long
enough to send the system to sleep, powering down peripherals A, B and C to
their low power state and other system resources (b). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-44F96E35-4DA5-5A34-8D12-6E99D4B96856"><p>The timer expires and
the system wakes up to the same power level as before (c). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-61124A91-05C6-589D-884B-F4CE5FF9A970"><p>The inactivity timer
implemented in the peripheral driver for peripheral A expires: the peripheral
is transitioned to the low power state (d). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-1A1BF422-6C3A-5F90-BB8E-E84A31478723"><p>At (e) the system enters
the idle thread again: the timer queue is investigated and then enters sleep
mode, waking up again when an interrupt occurs (f). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-14C0126F-4333-5A96-93CE-7BBA17A422EF"><p>The inactivity timer
associated with the peripheral drive for peripheral B expires and the peripheral
is transitioned to its low power state (g). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-3CC1A70B-832A-53EC-BD04-9FA58F58F97D"><p>On the next call to <codeph>CpuIdle()</codeph> the
time for the next timer expiration is not long enough to power off peripherals
and other system resources: only limited power savings can be made (h) until
the system wakes up again (i). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-FC9FE747-CF6D-501A-B36F-4776F53E5317"><p>Finally, the inactivity
timer for peripheral C expires and the peripheral is transitioned to low power
state (j). On reaching another period of system idle all conditions are met
to send the system to the deepest sleep mode available accompanied by the
switching off other power resources (k). </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-6E283027-9516-50AA-94A7-BEA5C1A1E115"><p>On waking up (l) the
system resources are restored to the same power level as before. </p> </li>
</ul> <p>Any transition to and from these low power states must be transparent
to the rest of the system. A transparent transition is one that can be instantly
reversed, perhaps automatically in hardware, and has no noticeable impact
on system performance. In other words, it should be possible to wake the processor
up and move the entire device to Active Mode as if coming from a “normal”
Idle Mode. </p> <p>To perform a system wide power change which is not transparent,
peripherals that may be affected by the transition would need to be examined,
and interfaces would have to be provided so that the users of these peripherals
could query the peripheral and allow or disallow the system transition into
that state. </p> </section>
</conbody></concept>