<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-D1F4B2DC-5B18-4454-BFD7-8BB61D80E7CA" xml:lang="en"><title>Special
character table</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Special character table consists of symbols other than alphanumeric letters
such as punctuation marks, currency symbols.</p>
<p>The special character table works with touch down and release. Special
character table is opened by:<ul>
<li><p>short pressing <i>* §key_star_key§</i> key in virtual ITU-T.</p></li>
<li><p>pressing the dedicated special character table button in handwriting
recognition.</p></li>
<li><p>pressing the dedicated special character table button in smiley picker.</p></li>
</ul>Special character table does not have title or traditional softkeys.</p>
<p>Orientation of special character table follows the orientation of the input
method. For example, if the special character table is opened from the full
screen QWERTY, the orientation is landscape. If the table is opened from smaller
QWERTY which is in portrait, the orientation of the table should also be portrait.
There is no focus in the grid but if evoked with hardware key event, focus
is brought to the first item of the most recently used character row. </p>
<p>The first row in the special character table consists of the Close button
and can consist of the Smiley picker button. Smiley picker button can be hidden
if needed by the application. The second row in the special character table
displays most recently used characters. In portrait mode, the row consists
of five items and in landscape, seven items. If characters cannot fit to one
page, a page navigator is opened. Through this page navigator, user can change
the page by tapping on the navigation arrows. Navigating arrows are looping
so that user can access from the last page to the first page and vice versa. </p>
<p>Special character table can be closed only by pressing the Close button.
When the special character table is in landscape, the page navigator is moved
to the top row next to the Close button. The amount of most recently used
characters is increased by two items so that the table fills the entire display.</p>
<fig id="GUID-C3DF380A-2419-46A8-B0D8-B81F162540F3">
<title>Special character table portrait and landscape mode</title>
<image href="GUID-7C87B04A-1CCC-47D2-9B53-4E341412EFD2_d0e98341_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p/>
<table id="GUID-A3962EAA-542C-48FC-93B6-C2D2686AA082"><title>Default touch
events to special character table.</title>
<tgroup cols="3">

<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.80*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.01*"/>
<colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.19*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry valign="top"><p>User action</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>State change</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>Feedback</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down</p></entry>
<entry><p>Inactive</p></entry>
<entry><p>Highlight is shown. </p><p>Tactile: Basic list effect and audio
feedback are provided with touch down event.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch release on grid item</p></entry>
<entry><p>Activates the selected item and closes the table.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Highlight disappears. </p><p>Tactile: Basic list effect is provided
with touch release event. No audio feedback is provided.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down on navigation arrow or smiley picker button</p></entry>
<entry><p>Button pressed effect.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect and audio feedback are provided with
touch down event.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch release on navigation arrow</p></entry>
<entry><p>Next or previous page of the table is opened.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect is provided with touch release event.
No audio feedback is provided.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch release on SCT button or smiley picker button</p></entry>
<entry><p>Special character table is opened and smiley picker is closed or
other way around.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect is provided with touch release event.
No audio feedback is provided.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release on close button</p></entry>
<entry><p>Table is closed, no characters are selected.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect is provided with touch release event.
No audio feedback is provided.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and move</p></entry>
<entry><p>Inactive</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: No effect</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></conbody></concept>