<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept xml:lang="en" id="GUID-178F91C8-32F4-5CD3-B81D-F0A6C45097E5"><title>Network PSY Overview</title><shortdesc>This document describes the Network PSY, which connects the Location Server (<codeph>eposserver.exe</codeph>) to the Network Location Manager. </shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody><section><title>Purpose</title> <p>The Network PSY connects the Location Server (<codeph>eposserver.exe</codeph>) to the Network Location Manager. It allows the Location Server to use the network to obtain cell-based position fixes. The PSY does not interface directly with the network. You must install a Network Protocol Module to use the Network PSY. </p> <p>This document is for device creators. </p> </section> <section><title>Required background</title> <p>This document assumes a knowledge of the material covered in the following: </p> <ul><li id="GUID-06CE28F8-A54D-5D72-92F5-2B8BC32373C1"><p><xref href="GUID-7233BC33-6060-5D6B-A5D2-01135F059337.dita">LBS Architecture Overview</xref>  </p> </li> <li id="GUID-7BEF2FE9-48A3-5B79-BDA7-543F38F18FCD"><p><xref href="GUID-D18B4715-3942-52EA-9D2F-E145037FA47A.dita">LBS Integration and Configuration Guide</xref>  </p> </li> </ul> </section> <section><title>Key concepts and terms</title> <dl><dlentry><dt>PSY</dt> <dd><p>A Positioning Plug-in. The Network PSY implements the Positioning Plug-in API to interface with the Location Server. It uses the Positioning Plug-in Information API (central repository key/value pairs) to register itself with the LBS subsystem. </p> </dd> </dlentry> <dlentry><dt>Network Protocol Module</dt> <dd><p>An ECom plug-in loaded by the Network Gateway. A Network Protocol Module connects the LBS subsystem to a network via the ETel or ESock communication stacks. </p> </dd> </dlentry> </dl> </section> <section><title>Architecture</title> <p>Figure 1 shows the Network PSY with associated LBS components. </p> <fig id="GUID-0CC6BDFE-4DDB-5F72-B233-6B239E311D96"><title>
             Figure 1. Network PSY with components on which it depends. 
          </title> <image href="GUID-E8E32DC5-EABC-5125-8EDA-718CF434E01C_d0e471312_href.png" placement="inline"/></fig> <p>The Network PSY implements the Positioning Plug-in API. The PSY does not interface directly with the network. It connects with the network via the Network Location Manager and a Network Protocol Module. To use the Network PSY, you must install a Network Protocol Module. </p> <p>The Network PSY is packaged in the library <filepath>lbsnetpsy.dll</filepath>. This DLL contains one ECom plug-in implementation of the PSY interface. </p> <p>If you include the Network PSY in your LBS ROM using the LBS <codeph>buildrom</codeph> macros, a file containing the central repository keys and values for the PSY is also included. The keys and values in the file register the PSY with the Location Server. The keys in the file are defined by the Positioning Plug-in Information API. </p> <p>The Network PSY appears as a normal PSY to the Location Server and is selected by Location Acquisition API client applications by UID, or by the Default PSY. </p> <p>See <xref href="GUID-6FE3CBB5-869E-5F45-B74D-E2C86BD3746B.dita">Network PSY Tutorial</xref> for an explanation of how to configure the PSY. </p> </section> <section><title>APIs</title> <p>The Network PSY implements the Positioning Plug-in API to integrate with the LBS subsystem. The code distribution for this PSY includes a central repository initialisation file that contains key/value pairs specified by the Positioning Plug-in Information API. </p> <p>The Network PSY does not provide any APIs. </p> </section> <section><title>Typical uses</title> <p>The Network PSY is used by the LBS Location Server <codeph>eposserver.exe</codeph> to obtain position fixes using cell-based positioning. The Network Gateway and Network Protocol Module are responsible for interfacing with a communication stack to obtain the position. </p> </section> </conbody><related-links><link href="GUID-A2721B54-9B0A-572E-A695-22058F627639.dita"><linktext>Network PSY
                Tutorial</linktext> </link> <link href="GUID-7233BC33-6060-5D6B-A5D2-01135F059337.dita"><linktext>LBS Architecture Overview</linktext> </link> <link href="GUID-D18B4715-3942-52EA-9D2F-E145037FA47A.dita"><linktext>LBS
                Integration and Configuration Guide</linktext> </link> <link href="GUID-85DD1F91-2430-5C86-A13A-8360DDCC4A2F.dita"><linktext>Positioning
                Plug-in API (PSY API)</linktext> </link> <link href="GUID-7CE5CF4C-7661-5FE1-87CA-CC4EB1CECE34.dita"><linktext>Default
                PSY</linktext> </link> </related-links></concept>