<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept xml:lang="en" id="GUID-AB397519-AE26-5DBC-8D00-1961E2E0F734"><title>A-GPS Location Manager Overview</title><shortdesc>The A-GPS Location Manager is responsible for obtaining a location from A-GPS hardware. </shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody><section><title>Purpose</title> <p>The A-GPS Location Manager is used by the Location Server and the Network Request Handler. It loads an A-GPS Integration Module to obtain positions from A-GPS hardware. </p> </section> <section><title>Required background</title> <p>The reader should be familiar with the <xref href="GUID-7233BC33-6060-5D6B-A5D2-01135F059337.dita">LBS architecture</xref>. </p> </section> <section><title>Key concepts and terms</title> <dl><dlentry><dt>Assisted GPS (A-GPS)</dt> <dd><p>A-GPS uses assistance data from the network to reduce the Time To First Fix (TTFF) </p> </dd> </dlentry> </dl> </section> <section><title>Architecture</title> <p>The A-GPS Location Manager is a process that runs as part of the LBS subsystem. It is responsible for obtaining a location from A-GPS hardware. </p> <p>The Location Server sends requests for location to the A-GPS Location Manager when the position quality criteria specified for an MO-LR (self locate) requires a GPS fix (or when no position quality criteria are specified). </p> <p>The Network Request Handler may send a request for location to the A-GPS Location Manager if the position quality criteria specified for an MT-LR or MO-LR (transmit to third party) requires a GPS fix. </p> <p>The A-GPS Location Manager obtains GPS data from GPS hardware through an A-GPS Integration Module. The A-GPS Location Manager also interacts with the Network Gateway to obtain assistance data from the network. </p> <fig id="GUID-691D4545-39EC-5785-9C23-4529094FF3C1"><title>
             Figure 1. A-GPS Location Manager.
          </title> <image href="GUID-F322F81A-40D3-5365-A437-73B60DD31D5E_d0e438257_href.png" placement="inline"/></fig> </section> <section><title>APIs</title> <p>The A-GPS Location Manager is an internal component of the LBS subsystem. It does not expose any published APIs. </p> </section> <section><title>Typical uses</title> <p>The A-GPS Location Manager is only used internally by the LBS subsystem. </p> </section> </conbody><related-links><link href="GUID-5DD17088-1F9C-5810-8143-5067A2B18330.dita"><linktext>A-GPS Location Data Source API</linktext> </link> <link href="GUID-B66A425F-3C65-5BF5-ADA2-E25EB7267681.dita"><linktext>A-GPS Reference Module</linktext> </link> </related-links></concept>