<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-A05B7A4D-EAE1-4E92-9337-8CA1CC5C0FAD" xml:lang="en"><title>WMDRM
Engine Overview</title><shortdesc>WMDRM Engine is a component of WMDRM collection. It provides interfaces
to perform WMDRM implementations, such as managing WMDRM licenses and decrypting
WMDRM content. Applications that require WMDRM functionality must interact
with WMDRM plug-ins and Camese components by implementing the interfaces provided
by WMDRM engine.</shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<section id="GUID-B4A696C6-F075-499D-B4C1-5058DA10930C"><title>Required Background</title><p>Before
you start, you must understand the following:</p><ul>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-84B6389A-55CC-53EB-8725-65F753FD7217.dita">Content Access
Framework (CAF) Overview</xref></p></li>
<li><p>Helix multimedia framework </p></li>
<li><p>MTP Framework</p></li>
</ul></section>
<section id="GUID-3396F235-AE9D-40B5-89CA-5B652AF80A6C"><title>Key concepts</title><ul>
<li><b>Camese</b>: It is the Over-the-air (OTA) download protocol for WMDRM
licenses.</li>
<li><b>Secure clock</b>: The clock is for use by secure DRM applications which
has TCB capability. For more information, see <xref href="GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7.dita#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7/GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7#GUID-CD506806-FC59-547A-B5CD-03314DF847F7">Date and Time Handling Overview</xref>.</li>
</ul></section>
<section id="GUID-39DA53FB-F762-4B79-82C5-E5A849CCB94A"><title>Description</title> 
     <p>WMDRM Engine comprises the following five sub-components:<ul>
<li><p><b>WMDRM CAF Agent</b>: WMDRM CAF Agent implements the CAF Agent interface
and plug-in. It allows obtaining rights status information and metadata, and
provides a way to delete the data storage as an agent-specific functionality.<note> It
does not provide functionality to read the decrypted data from ASF content
files due to their packetized nature.</note></p></li>
<li><p><b>ASF</b>: ASF is used to read data from ASF files by WMDRM CAF Agent
and WMDRM Over The Air (OTA) plug-in.</p></li>
<li><p><b>WMDRM Porting Kit Server</b>: WMDRM Porting Kit Server allows you
to access functions of the porting kit without the need for DRM capability.
For example, to add new usage rights or to check the rights status. It also
allows you to access the device certificate and unique id from WMDRM Key Storage.
It implements the UI functionality required to be displayed, when license
store becomes full or needs to be deleted.</p><note>The Symbian
platform does not provide implementation of WMDRM Porting Kit Server. Device
creators must provide their own implementation for WMDRM Porting Kit Server. </note></li>
<li><p><b>WMDRM Server</b>: The WMDRM Server includes the following functionalities: <ul>
<li><p>It manages porting kit data in an encrypted form using SQL database.</p></li>
<li><p>It implements the data storage functionality and an anti-rollback clock
needed for enforcement of time-based licenses.</p></li>
<li><p>It provides data store state functionality for WMDRM Porting Kit Server.
The state information of data store is used to inform the device user to continue
synchronizing WMDRM contents to the phone, when the data store runs out of
space.</p></li>
<li><p>It provides data storage deletion functionality for WMDRM Porting Kit
Server and WMDRM CAF Agent.</p></li>
</ul></p></li>
<li><p><b>WMDRM File Server</b>: The WMDRM File Server has TCB capability
and includes the following functionalities:<ul>
<li><p>It manages encrypted files in the path <codeph>c:\sys\private\200b180\</codeph> </p></li>
<li><p>It handles low level file server interaction </p></li>
<li><p>It handles data backwards compatibility and updates the secure time.
The <i>secure time</i> can be set using System Static Functions API. </p></li>
</ul></p></li>
</ul><fig id="GUID-F470FE96-4BB5-489F-88F1-BDD6291BEB69">
<image href="GUID-21562C58-896C-48B0-A574-975E1326A93A_d0e171368_href.jpg" placement="inline"/>
</fig></p><note>To make the WMDRM content
fully functional, device creators must license the WMDRM porting kit from
Microsoft and integrate it.</note>     </section>

</conbody></concept>