<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-90DF40EF-7D3F-551D-9957-A3756317A254" xml:lang="en"><title>OCSP
Overview</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP) is an internet protocol that
determines whether a given <xref href="GUID-911E9F7E-D0AD-55EC-A3F4-1D427F803780.dita">certificate</xref> or
a list of certificates has been revoked, and therefore, determines whether
the certificate can be trusted. The protocol is defined in <xref href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2560.txt" scope="external">RFC2560</xref>. </p>
<p>On the Symbian platform, <xref href="GUID-0AED3485-D498-57F1-9532-116EA5C8F68B.dita">Secure
Software Install (SWI)</xref> uses OCSP to verify whether a certificate associated
with an application to be installed has been revoked. For details of how SWI
uses OCSP revocation check, see <xref href="GUID-C893C9E6-47B8-5149-9808-0274C61CF3D7.dita">OCSP
SWI Integration</xref>. </p>
<section id="GUID-F07B2071-BF8B-4D22-B6F6-1282B2040376"><title>OCSP request and response</title> <p>OCSP primarily consists
of two parts: a request and a response, each specified in the Abstract Syntax
Notation One - Distinguished Encoding Rules (<xref href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4792" scope="external">ASN.1</xref> -DER) format. A client application that wants
to get information on the revocation status of a certificate, forms an OCSP
request and sends this to an OCSP server. In its simplest form, an OCSP request
consists of one or more identifiers for the certificates whose status is in
question. The request is sent to the OCSP server identified by a Uniform Resource
Identifier (URI). The URI is specified either in the Authority Information
Access (AIA) extension of the certificate whose revocation status is to be
checked, or as a global URI with the OCSP client. AIA is defined in <xref href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2459.txt" scope="external">RFC2459</xref>. </p> <p>The
OCSP server maintains information about the revocation of certificates. The
server replies to the client with a signed OCSP response, mentioning the revocation
status for each certificate. A response being signed with a key pair is trusted
as authoritative by the client. Alternatively, a server can also return an
error code as response (refer to <xref href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2560.txt" scope="external">RFC2560</xref> for details of the various OCSP errors). OCSP
is transport-neutral with the URI of the server indicating the required transport
mechanism. Currently, only Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is supported. </p> <p>The
client, in turn, verifies whether the response is valid and is from a trusted
entity. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-B4A093DA-6968-4B17-A3A7-7FF4800DED3B"><title>OCSP client-server interaction</title> <p>The server to which
the request for revocation check is sent may not actually be the server which
is authoritative to answer the request, but may act as a proxy to the destination
server. For information on the server to which the request actually gets routed,
the client includes a <i>serviceLocator</i> extension (containing the URI)
in the OCSP request. </p> <p>There may be a <i>serviceLocator</i> extension
for each certificate in the request. Therefore, it is syntactically possible
for the request to be split into multiple parts, with each part routed to
a different OCSP responder (the server that actually responds to the OCSP
request). The intermediate server collates the individual responses into one
and returns this to the client. This response is signed only by the intermediate
server. In such a situation, the client must trust this intermediate server. </p> <p>Three
scenarios are associated with the routing of OCSP requests to the appropriate
responder through intermediate servers. They are as follows: </p> <ul>
<li id="GUID-CD8AAEA0-AA94-58EA-978F-3C2E21A2FE9F"><p> <b>Single OCSP responder</b>  </p> <p>One
OCSP server contains the revocation information for all the certificates to
be checked. One request containing all the certificates is sent to the responder
(in this case, the OCSP server), which replies with a single response. The
following figure illustrates the interaction between the OCSP client and a
single destination responder. </p> <fig id="GUID-11F6D229-29D0-510A-AB8A-64A906DC00F7">
<image href="GUID-8E3F3745-7875-51A2-BDA1-AA537C7B220E_d0e644296_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> </li>
<li id="GUID-185C0C91-CC3F-5198-8EAB-BB1BF748A3D0"><p> <b>Multiple OCSP responders
using an intermediate OCSP server</b>  </p> <p>Multiple OCSP responders use
an intermediate OCSP server to route requests to the appropriate destination
responders. One request is sent to the intermediate server, which sends multiple
individual requests to the destination responders. The responses are collated,
and one response is sent back to the client. The following figure shows the
interaction between an OCSP client and multiple destination responders by
using an intermediate responder. </p> <fig id="GUID-964E18AA-E4F7-5A71-A2F3-19F3007C24C6">
<image href="GUID-2EF123C9-62A2-52FF-9792-66EF41F37452_d0e644312_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> </li>
<li id="GUID-F092252F-79EF-58E2-A596-77D3FC07CC54"><p> <b>Multiple OCSP responders
without an intermediate server</b>  </p> <p>The client does the work of sending
each request to the appropriate responder. The client collates the responses
received. The following figure shows the interaction between the client and
multiple destination responders. </p> <fig id="GUID-223A3DB6-538E-5A4E-946C-87AA03449857">
<image href="GUID-A6F1F6AC-5D3C-5055-AEF1-B64671941BCB_d0e644328_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> </li>
</ul> <p>The choice of the correct method of interaction between the client
and the responders depends on the nature of the Public Key Infrastructure
(PKI) and the availability of OCSP responders for routing requests as intermediates. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-891303A3-070F-40D2-9382-40A1165928DE"><title>Revocation check results</title> <p>If the response sent by
the OCSP server passes all the validation, the application that sends the
OCSP request determines the outcome by applying the following rules to the
certificate statuses in the response: </p> <ul>
<li id="GUID-124E3CDE-7F74-5960-A92C-98B101644036"><p>If any certificate is
revoked, the result is <b>Revoked</b>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-C0AF0A69-28C4-528B-9E14-1AAF13CEA497"><p>If all certificates
are valid, the result is <b>Good</b>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-7BA5DACD-19B1-55CC-9378-28F4A47AAE12"><p>Otherwise, the result
is <b>Unknown</b>. </p> </li>
</ul> <p> <b>Note:</b> A certificate status of <b>Good</b> does not indicate
that the certificate may be trusted. It merely indicates that the certificate
has not been revoked. The normal validation of that certificate (or the <xref href="GUID-A3B58436-07E4-565B-800B-86435D205461.dita">certificate chain</xref> in
which it lies) must still be performed. </p> </section>
</conbody><related-links>
<link href="GUID-C893C9E6-47B8-5149-9808-0274C61CF3D7.dita"><linktext>OCSP SWI
Integration</linktext></link>
</related-links></concept>