<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-BFEEECCA-190B-4DDE-8A04-4FE918BE8690" xml:lang="en"><title>Options
menu</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>The <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu is a tool that offers the user
a set of possible functions in the current context. Pressing the left softkey
labeled <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> opens the <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu.</p>
<fig id="GUID-DE323941-E70E-4169-9F67-6E7A11047481">
<title>Options menu</title>
<image href="GUID-8BA0D643-5ED1-4DC4-82EC-C8AA392DCBC4_d0e90134_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>The <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu is a menu list displayed in a pop-up
window. An item is selected by pressing either the left softkey (<uicontrol>Select</uicontrol>)
or the Selection key. An item can also be selected directly from the list.
The user must either select an item from the list or cancel the menu; it cannot
be left pending during another action (see <xref href="GUID-0BAE2D0E-604B-4A62-B5EB-AC68EAF7F589.dita">Navigating
in applications</xref>).</p>
<p><uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu items that are item-specific and require
an item on the screen to be focused, are not displayed in the <b>Options</b> menu
unless user has opened the Options menu while navigating the UI with hardware
keys. The item specific commands are hidden in the <b>Options</b> menu while
moving with touch, and are made visible when activating the hardware interaction.
The item specific commands are not updated or removed, while the <b>Options</b> menu
is open.</p>
<p>Items in the <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu use the single item layout;
that is, they are text-only. The number of items in the menu is not limited,
because the list scrolls as necessary. The <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> always
loops, which allows users to easily reach the end of the list.</p>
<table id="GUID-F71BE5D4-D757-476F-811A-E3364937E3DB"><title>Default touch
events for Options menu</title>
<tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.80*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.01*"/><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.19*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry valign="top"><p>User action</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>State change</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>Feedback</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>

<entry><p>Touch down (no sub-menu for the item)</p></entry>
<entry><p>No effect. </p><p><note> Submenu behaves similarly as the main menu.</note></p></entry>
<entry><p>Highlight is shown. </p><p>Tactile: Basic list effect and audio
feedback is provided with touch down event.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch release (no sub-menu for the item)</p></entry>
<entry><p>The focused item is activated and <b>Options</b> menu closed.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Highlight disappears. </p><p>Tactile: Basic list effect is provided
with touch release event.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release (when sub-menu available for the item)</p></entry>
<entry><p>A submenu is opened. </p><p>The <b>Options</b> menu item for which
the submenu was opened from (that is, parent item) must be visible.</p></entry>
<entry><p>The parent item stays highlighted while the submenu is open to show
the relation between the two. </p><p>The submenu does not have highlight unless
it was opened with a hardware key. </p><p>Tactile: Basic list effect and audio
feedback is provided with touch down and basic list effect with release event.
For pop-up related tactile feedback, normal pop-up effect when opening and
closing if the theme effects are OFF. If they are ON, then increasing long
touch is used when opening and pop-up close effect when closing.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down on <b>Options</b> menu and move out of the <b>Options</b> menu</p></entry>
<entry><p>Refer to <xref href="GUID-7C61D3D7-8FCB-46AB-B2E9-CE1AC68F86DE.dita">Dragging
and flicking</xref> events</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Refer to <xref href="GUID-7C61D3D7-8FCB-46AB-B2E9-CE1AC68F86DE.dita">Dragging
and flicking</xref> events.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release outside the <b>Options</b> menu</p></entry>
<entry><p>Inactive</p></entry>
<entry><p>If there is hardware highlight, it disappears. </p><p>Tactile: No
effect</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release outside menu area when sub-menu is open</p></entry>
<entry><p>Only the sub-menu is closed, main menu remains open.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Highlight disappears from the parent menu item. </p><p>Tactile:
Pop-up effect and sensitive audio feedback is provided with touch down event.
If theme effects are ON, pop-up close effect is given with touch release.
Else, no tactile feedback is provided with touch release.</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<section id="GUID-FF69390C-BA3D-47D5-A0C9-031CBA2464FC"><title>Using
the Options menu in applications</title><p>The API to use for the <uicontrol>Options</uicontrol> menu
is the <xref format="html" href="specs/guides/Options_Menu_API_Specification/Options_Menu_API_Specification.html" scope="peer">Options menu API</xref>. For implementation information, see <xref format="html" href="specs/guides/Options_Menu_API_Specification/Options_Menu_API_Specification.html#Options_Menu_API_Specification.topic3" scope="peer">Using the Options menu API</xref>.</p></section>
</conbody></concept>