<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8" xml:lang="en"><title>Interrupts
Concepts</title><shortdesc>An interrupt is a condition that causes the CPU to suspend normal
execution, enter the interrupt handling state and jump to a section of code
called an interrupt handler. </shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>An interrupt source is a hardware device or software action that can force
the CPU to enter the interrupt handling state. </p>
<p>Typically, a number of interrupt sources are monitored by an interrupt
controller. This is hardware that generates a single interrupt notification
to the CPU, and provides information about which interrupts are pending, which
means which interrupts require action to be taken. </p>
<ul>
<li id="GUID-DC5F0973-1F7A-54AF-93D9-6B100A36A873"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-F5C1C873-B922-53F1-81D7-1924A5FC6FBC">ISR</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-B736A016-3845-5675-916E-9271437CEA55"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-EABF9C68-0404-51DA-BCD1-B2E712A33240">Interrupt ID</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-6A3BCC00-6682-5E80-B5FC-B45E7C948989"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-EAA4FC86-DCEF-5B42-BD4E-AF9941DE35B0">Binding and unbinding</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-A8E91BB3-ECF0-5401-B797-5687B54820B2"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-AE50D050-E28B-572C-8D35-CB8ECEBC5706">Dispatching interrupts</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-2A683414-EE91-58EF-85AF-0613645E3072"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-311851FE-884D-5FAA-A2AE-548F44FFB03B">Chained and shared interrupts</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-FE7BCE49-A01D-5EC0-98C5-5B5148BBCCF8"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-8C39B9F9-78F7-5329-B06D-3CD2F715E270">Variant interrupts</xref>  </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-B08675CF-66F0-5B9A-943D-B5DB41B5C58D"><p> <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-310D362D-4778-55A1-B6D9-9059CF9E23E0">IRQs, FIQs and interrupt priority</xref>  </p> </li>
</ul>
<section id="GUID-F5C1C873-B922-53F1-81D7-1924A5FC6FBC"><title>ISR</title> <p>An <i>interrupt
service routine</i>, or ISR, is code that deals with a pending interrupt.
The Symbian platform kernel responds to an interrupt notification by calling
an ISR for each pending interrupt. The process of calling ISRs is called interrupt
dispatch. </p> <p>There must be an ISR associated with every interrupt that
must be handled on a device; if an interrupt occurs that does not have an
associated ISR, the kernel panics with a spurious interrupt error. By default,
the baseport ensures that all interrupts are bound to, what is called, the
spurious interrupt handler. Typically, this is a short piece of code that
faults the system indicating the number of the interrupt. </p> <p>In EKA2,
the ISR may either be a standalone function or a static class member. </p> <p>Each
ISR takes a single 32-bit parameter that is, typically, a pointer to an instance
of the owning class, although it can be any value that is appropriate. The
parameter is defined as a <xref href="GUID-6D079976-9119-31FA-8E21-C3B815F94648.dita"><apiname>TAny</apiname></xref> * type, so a cast is almost
always necessary. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-EABF9C68-0404-51DA-BCD1-B2E712A33240"><title>Interrupt ID</title> <p>An
interrupt source is identified by number, defined as a <xref href="GUID-7A2A43EC-6125-3BFE-834B-23C37F7B40D5.dita"><apiname>TInt</apiname></xref> type.
Typically, the ASSP layer defines this number for each interrupt in a header
file and exports it so that it can be included and used by device drivers. </p> <p>Where
the ASSP layer is split into a common layer and a variant (device specific)
layer, then the variant layer may also define its own set of interrupt IDs. </p> <p>This
number is usually referred to as the interrupt ID. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-EAA4FC86-DCEF-5B42-BD4E-AF9941DE35B0"><title>Binding and
unbinding</title> <p>The action of associating an ISR with an interrupt source
is called binding, and an ISR is said to be bound to the interrupt. ISRs are
bound dynamically, that is, at runtime. You can also unbind an ISR and bind
a different ISR. </p> <p> <b>Note</b>: only one ISR can be bound to an interrupt
source at any one time. </p> <p>A device driver binds an ISR by calling <xref href="GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3.dita#GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3/GUID-4E3CB472-3525-32F8-9BC4-8ECFEE931E7B"><apiname>Interrupt::Bind()</apiname></xref>,
passing the interrupt source ID; similarly, the device driver can unbind the
ISR by calling <xref href="GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3.dita#GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3/GUID-CCC9A397-608C-3EAF-830F-A59800C2E8E5"><apiname>Interrupt::Unbind()</apiname></xref>, also passing the <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-EABF9C68-0404-51DA-BCD1-B2E712A33240">interrupt
ID</xref>. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-AE50D050-E28B-572C-8D35-CB8ECEBC5706"><title>Dispatching
interrupts</title> <p>When an interrupt occurs, it first invokes code in the
kernel that prepares the system to run the interrupt by switching to a safe
stack and storing some state information. It then launches code called the
interrupt dispatcher (often just referred to as the dispatcher) which, as
the name suggests, is responsible for determining which interrupts need to
be serviced and calling the appropriate ISRs. </p> <p>At its simplest, this
is the process of deciding which interrupts are pending and calling the ISR
for each. This is the general principle: </p> <codeblock id="GUID-C871D02B-5211-5152-989B-6D34C039F7C5" xml:space="preserve">
    {
       FOREVER
              {
        Get next pending interrupt;
        if None
            {
               return;
            }
        call ISR for the pending interrupt;
        }
    }
</codeblock> <p>In general, however, when you are writing code that uses the
interrupt, you don't need to worry about the work that goes on "behind the
scenes" that calls your ISR. However, if the interrupt is shared by a number
of peripherals, or there are multiple levels of hardware interrupt controllers,
then you might need to consider the behaviour of the dispatcher – these are
called "Chained and shared interrupts". </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-311851FE-884D-5FAA-A2AE-548F44FFB03B"><title>Chained and
shared interrupts</title> <p>The functions in the <xref href="GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3.dita"><apiname>Interrupt</apiname></xref> class
give a <i>flat</i> view of the interrupts in the system. In fact, this may
not be the true organisation, and groups of interrupts may be handled by separate
hardware that is wired together or <i>chained</i>. </p> <fig id="GUID-5BE80A1D-CD61-536B-A304-2B5EA54A9566">
<title>              Chained interrupts            </title>
<image href="GUID-9FAFEF6D-4CBC-5EBB-8BA9-B5480478F4A7_d0e270169_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> <p>A system may have multiple interrupt controllers to handle a large
number of interrupt sources. They are usually prioritised by connecting the
interrupt output of one interrupt controller to an interrupt input of another
interrupt controller. </p> <p>If several sources of interrupts share a single
interrupt line, then the ISRs for each interrupt source are bound to a pseudo-interrupt,
meaning that the interrupt Id is a fake interrupt provided by the interrupt
dispatcher. If the dispatcher cannot conveniently determine which source has
signalled the interrupt, it just calls all ISRs bound to this set of pseudo-interrupts. </p> <fig id="GUID-3AA2C613-35C0-5C4B-B4D2-2FD1207E21AA">
<title>              Shared interrupts            </title>
<image href="GUID-C5D3FE0C-8151-5780-8D72-016146D58853_d0e270183_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> <p>An interrupt Id should not be confused with an interrupt line, especially,
when interrupt lines are shared. However, if the interrupt line is not shared
then the interrupt Id is the same value as the interrupt line and may be explicitly
defined within headers. </p> <p>If the interrupt is shared then: </p> <ul>
<li id="GUID-7A28A243-B5B7-5687-97EE-6C79FDFA6411"><p>the first time an ISR
is bound to an interrupt line the interrupt Id can be the same value </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-7C01181A-C61B-51B7-9969-ADEE2619967D"><p>for each subsequent
attempt to bind an ISR to an interrupt line, its interrupt Id will differ
from the interrupt line number. </p> </li>
</ul> <p>This Interrupt Id should be used explicitly when refering to ISR-related
functions. In general, as a user of the interrupt you probably don't need
to know the actual structure underlying the interrupts, but you do need to
be aware of these points: </p> <ul>
<li id="GUID-6680525A-6E24-5CD3-B105-BE185390FD7F"><p>Interrupts further down
a chain may have a longer dispatch latency, that is, the time between the
interrupt signalling and the ISR being called. </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-EE5F4275-3746-5EC6-9B82-8AA23F47D5B2"><p>If a peripheral shares
an interrupt line with a number of other peripherals, an ISR that services
that peripheral may be called even if the peripheral hasn't raised an interrupt.
Just because your ISR is called, you cannot assume that the peripheral it
services has generated the interrupt. </p> </li>
</ul> </section>
<section id="GUID-8C39B9F9-78F7-5329-B06D-3CD2F715E270"><title>Variant interrupts</title> <p>Variant
interrupts are just a special case of <xref href="GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8.dita#GUID-709C26A7-3724-52A8-ACA1-619BD241E6B8/GUID-311851FE-884D-5FAA-A2AE-548F44FFB03B">Chained
and shared interrupts</xref>, where the chained interrupt controller is actually
provided on hardware external to the core processor. The comments applying
to chained interrupts apply equally to Variant interrupts. </p> <p>The definition
of the interrupt ID number will be in a header file provided by the Variant,
but note that the interrupt may not exist on all hardware. </p> <p>If your
device driver is intended to run on several variants, not all of which have
a particular interrupt, then you need to ensure that you only attempt to use
this interrupt where it exists. Alternatively, if the driver is only intended
to run on hardware with that interrupt, then it may be sensible for the driver
code to raise a panic if it is run on the wrong hardware; this will clearly
indicate that the driver is incompatible with the hardware. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-310D362D-4778-55A1-B6D9-9059CF9E23E0"><title>IRQs, FIQs
and interrupt priority</title> <p>The ARM processor supports two levels of
interrupt, IRQ and FIQ (<i>Fast IRQ</i>). FIQs have priority over IRQs. </p> <p>Sometimes,
interrupt sources are permanently configured as IRQ or FIQ, either by hardware
design or by software configuration. Often the hardware allows interrupts
to generate either an IRQ or a FIQ, and this can be configured using the <xref href="GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3.dita#GUID-E7A7083C-97B9-39B9-A147-4A6E314EE3A3/GUID-FA4CFED7-D694-399C-8F84-FA9FE3C3A171"><apiname>Interrupt::SetPriority()</apiname></xref> function,
but you need to check this with the baseport because it may not provide this
capability even though the hardware supports it. </p> <p> <codeph>Interrupt::SetPriority()</codeph> is
more powerful that just letting you configure IRQs and FIQs. Some interrupt
controllers allow the relative priority of each interrupt source in the system
to be modified instead of being hardwired in a specific order. <codeph>Interrupt::SetPriority()</codeph> therefore
takes a <codeph>TInt</codeph> type as the priority value, and the baseport
will define the meaning of this depending on what level of configurability
is provided. If interrupt priority cannot be changed <codeph>Interrupt::SetPriority()</codeph> will
return <codeph>KErrNotSupported</codeph>. You will need to check whether your
baseport supports configurable interrupt priority. </p> </section>
</conbody></concept>