<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-9665C072-EA52-54B8-87A3-A7F818940DCD" xml:lang="en"><title>What
is the CommsDat API</title><shortdesc>This topic is an intrdouction to the CommsDat API. Tools and applications
use the CommsDat API to access the data in the Comms Database. </shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>The CommsDat DLL implements the CommsDat API. Symbian platform
loads the CommsDat DLL at boot time. Tools and applications do not load the
DLL. </p>
<p>The API made available by the CommsDat DLL is the only method that users
can use to access the data in the Comms Database. The API maps between client-side
representations of the data and the data stored in the database. </p>
<p>Tools and applications see the data as a set of tables. A table is a set
of records, where each record is an ordered set of fields. Each field holds
a specified piece of information. A field at a given position in a record
contains the same type of data in all records. You can consider that each
field at a given location in a record is in a column. A table can also be
called a record set. </p>
<fig id="GUID-5ABD88C0-67E4-5091-BE8F-56ABFED4FEC8">
<image href="GUID-F7BFE6E3-0EEE-536C-8411-65D8F5FEBF2E_d0e111857_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>Tables, records, columns and fields are all CommsDat elements. An element
is an item that can be stored in the Comms Database. </p>
<p>The CommsDat API gives tools and applications a set of classes to retrieve,
create and change the elements in the Comms Database. The API also gives the
functionality to access the Comms Database. </p>
<p> </p>
</conbody><related-links>
<link href="GUID-B89D2828-0FEE-5206-97D2-C7D4BBD35799.dita"><linktext>How is the
                Comms Database secured</linktext></link>
</related-links></concept>