<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-86AADA3E-B77C-45CC-B523-785B75BAA5AA" xml:lang="en"><title>Menu</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Mobile device users can use the Menu to access applications. Pressing the
Home / Menu key opens the Menu, where the user may browse and select an application.
The Menu was previously called <i>Application Shell</i> and the Home / Menu
key was called <i>Applications key</i>. In addition to direct access to applications,
related applications can be collected in folders.</p>
<p>Applications are presented as a grid of items by default. User can select
a customized version of the Menu layout, such as a list. The default grid
layout is 3 x 4 (portrait) or 4 x 3 (landscape), that is 12 icons. Pressing
the Selection key opens an application and closes the Menu.</p>
<fig id="GUID-80CBAFCA-F952-4C96-8738-02D82261F4B4">
<title>Menu with a 3 x 4 grid in portrait (left) and 4 x 3 grid in landscape
(right)</title>
<image href="GUID-A69D2707-CB47-42C2-A6E9-5FB9BD86A30B_d0e90947_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>For more details on the landscape orientation, see <xref href="GUID-685C3F33-1530-4984-B125-E4EF8EBB2EE8.dita">Symbian
UI with rotation</xref>.</p>
<section id="GUID-D50A0D9B-B093-4529-971A-7239FFBA0880"><title>Shortcuts</title>When
the Menu is opened, numeric keys 1-9 can be used as shortcuts to select an
application. The keys are mapped directly to the nine icons in Menu’s initial
view, so that the Numeric key 1 corresponds to the top-left application and
the Numeric key 9 to the bottom-right one.</section>
<section id="GUID-84905F51-FD23-48EB-9C36-2022DB91DDF5"><title>Customizing
Menu</title><p>The user can organize the order of applications, create folders
and move applications into folders within the Menu. The folders created in
a Menu are customizable (the user can add and remove folders) and can have
unlimited sub-folders to allow a hierarchically organized structures. The
customizing functions are available in the <b>Options</b> menu. In addition,
the layout of the Menu can also be customized.</p></section>
</conbody></concept>