<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-971C9B81-1D6F-59E7-9416-385A0787D642" xml:lang="en"><title>The
control stack</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>The control stack is a mechanism provided by the control framework for
handling key press events. The Window Server, which generates events for control
framework applications, channels all key press events to the application that
currently has keyboard focus (Strictly speaking it channels key press events
to the <keyword>window group</keyword> ). It is up to the application itself
to channel the event to the correct destination as the Window Server does
not associate a key press event with a particular control. </p>
<p>In control framework applications using the <keyword>standard app     
   UI</keyword> the control stack contains a list of controls that wish to
receive keyboard events. Controls are added to the stack using <codeph>CCoeAppUi::AddToStackL()</codeph> and
their ordering on the stack determines their priority in receiving key events:
The one with the lowest position on the stack receiving key events first.
When a key press event occurs, it is offered to each control on the stack
in turn until it is consumed (i.e. used by that control). </p>
<p>The ordering of controls on the stack is determined by their priority,
a value passed to <codeph>CCoeAppUi::AddToStackL()</codeph>. If several controls
on the stack have the same priority, their ordering is determined by the order
in which they were added to the stack. </p>
<codeblock id="GUID-02BC135C-66C4-5FBD-9085-2F6946A24660" xml:space="preserve">enum
    {
    ECoeStackPriorityDefault=0,  // Low Priority
    ECoeStackPriorityMenu=10,
    ECoeStackPriorityDialog=50,
    ECoeStackPriorityCba=60,
    ECoeStackPriorityAlert=200,
    ECoeStackPriorityFep=250,
    ECoeStackPriorityEnvironmentFilter=300  // High Priority
    };
</codeblock>
<p>The diagram below shows a hypothetical stack containing 4 controls added
in the following order: control A (priority <codeph>ECoeStackPriorityDialog</codeph>),
control B (<codeph>ECoeStackPriorityMenu</codeph>), control C (<codeph>ECoeStackPriorityDefault</codeph> —
used for application views) and control D (<codeph>ECoeStackPriorityDialog</codeph>). </p>
<fig id="GUID-02308139-5BC5-5098-BE15-178434158843">
<title>           Example showing the order and priority of controls on the
control stack                    </title>
<image href="GUID-7AC4C1C2-D796-508F-93CF-21F061F49A30_d0e79010_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>On the stack shown in the diagram key-press events will be offered first
to control D, followed by A, B and C in that order. A control on the stack
can refuse key press events by setting a flag. This might be done by a dialogs
when it is not visible. </p>
<p>Applications use the control stack to channel key press events to destinations
in decreasing order of priority, such as: </p>
<ul>
<li id="GUID-EA1211C7-F2F1-5469-8EEB-66D44BC7542D"><p>debug keys </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-D4063EC0-102F-563D-9D56-84760F447F7A"><p>any active dialog </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-1ABFD001-B3A4-55C1-9D6A-F268457B8619"><p>any menu bar (i.e.,
its <keyword>hot-keys</keyword>) </p> </li>
<li id="GUID-DAD2BC72-CC2A-501A-BD40-E2234D4AE1F2"><p>the application view </p> </li>
</ul>
</conbody></concept>