<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-48482288-B60B-477A-8E28-132F7CBE2C94" xml:lang="en"><title>Confirmation
query</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>A confirmation query requests the user to confirm an operation, or asks
a Yes-No-type of question. It can be used e.g. to make sure that the user
does not accidentally delete important information or start an operation which
cannot be cancelled.</p>
<p>The layout for a Confirmation query is the same as the note layout, with
an optional graphic item.</p>
<p>One or two softkey labels can be used. In case the query can cause two
different consequences, the positive choice (<b>Yes</b>) is placed on the
left softkey, and the negative one (<b>No</b>) on the right softkey. In pure
confirmations, only one way to proceed is possible, and the response text
(for example <b>OK</b>) is placed on the left softkey.</p>
<p>The Selection key always causes the same action as the left softkey.</p>
<fig id="GUID-F5C18BD7-D656-4769-B841-C636628E9B1C">
<title>Confirmation query</title>
<image href="GUID-0DEC4D1B-2CD6-49BC-92E4-F0CB0BCBFA9D_d0e61865_href.jpg" scale="40" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>Guidelines for designing Confirmation queries:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>When designing the prompt text, make sure that the positive answer
is also a safe one. Users tend to proceed pressing the left softkey or the
Selection key without thinking too much. </p></li>
<li><p>Redundant Confirmation queries should be avoided. Do not add a Confirmation
query if there already are other forms of feedback, unless it is crucial that
the user gets a certain piece of information.</p></li>
</ul>
<section><title>Using confirmation queries
in C++ applications</title><p>For implementation information, see <xref href="GUID-7B275129-5EF7-4B27-B603-3BDE2C650A93.dita">Queries</xref>.</p></section>
</conbody></concept>