<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
	Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->  <!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd"><concept id="GUID-411ACFE6-0324-4330-ABCD-97A925759A3C" xml:lang="en"><title>Resource
management example: HelloWorldBasic</title><prolog><metadata><keywords></keywords></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>This section uses the <i>HelloWorldBasic</i> example provided with the
Symbian SDK to illustrate some of the basic issues associated
with using resource files when making applications for the Symbian OS. In
particular, this section explains the contents of the resource and registration
resource files used in the <i>HelloWorldBasic</i> application in terms of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-6AD1DA34-EA3D-4EC9-A667-390507B4D6CB.dita">helloworldbasic.rss</xref></p>
</li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-C99BA704-4E9F-482C-942F-1B4D7F385BD8.dita">HelloWorldBasic_reg.rss</xref></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The <i>HelloWorldBasic</i> application, in addition to printing "Hello
World!" on the screen, also demonstrates displaying text with Information
Note and loading strings with the help of StringLoader,
writing to and reading from a file and use of a dialog to inquire for user
input. Furthermore, the <i>HelloWorldBasic</i> application has been localized
to four different languages.</p>
<p>For more information about the available example applications, see the
Symbian SDK example folder at:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><parmname>&lt;S60_SDK_installation_directory&gt;\S60CppExamples\</parmname></p>
</li>
</ul>
<note>
<p>The application documentation is in the <parmname>doc</parmname> subfolder.</p>
</note>
<p>The other parts of this example are commented in <xref href="GUID-84D864EE-D893-43EC-A191-560FC74BF74B.dita"></xref>.</p>
<p>For more information about resource files, see <xref href="GUID-0FB60233-993A-4BF2-9E8C-E03AD092359B.dita">Managing
resource files</xref>.</p>
<section id="GUID-CE8A3826-F7DE-4E3C-96A3-53ABA03776CF"><title>Pre-requisites</title>
<p>The example can be found in the Symbian SDK and can be compiled and
run with the accompanying command line tools.</p>
<p>It is also recommended that you have a target device to which you can
deploy the application. </p>
<p>For more information on the software requirements for compiling and
running <i>HelloWorldBasic</i>, see <xref href="GUID-8DB6E28B-C49D-41D5-A563-A7D7CE3DF652.dita"></xref>.</p>
</section>
</conbody></concept>