<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-E7EFAD50-3323-49A6-A5D9-95B95F0FBF0E" xml:lang="en"><title>Preview
pop-up</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Preview pop-up is a floating component used for displaying more detailed
data about an item that has focus in the main pane.</p>
<fig id="GUID-443FE00D-6678-4951-9038-07C82D10B69E">
<title>Preview pop-up</title>
<image href="GUID-02072A1B-6F60-457B-8F26-2B25A6EA7C5F_d0e62363_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>The preview is displayed with a 0.6 second delay after the focus is moved
(for example, scrolling down a list with the Arrow keys) to avoid too rapid
and continuous flicker. The default time-out for closing the preview pop-up
is the same as for the Information pop-up, but it is possible to adjust it
if necessary.</p>
<p>Preview pop-up contents cannot be scrolled and the component must not contain
any buttons or other elements that make it appear interactive: the component
is the same in both standard and touch-enabled devices and should the component
be used in a standard non-touch device, its elements should not look touch-enabled.
There can be a maximum of five text rows in a preview pop-up, and it is possible
to place a small icon in the start of the rows. It is even possible to have
more than one icon on a row instead of text, if necessary. The number of images
in a single preview pop-up is limited to one, and it can be accompanied by
up to two rows of text.</p>
<p>Preview pop-up shows always duplicate data in a given application to ensure
that the user will not miss any content or functionality even if a given product
does not utilize preview pop-up (that is, it has been switched OFF). Owing
to the special nature of preview pop-up, it is important to thoroughly consider
its genuine usefulness in various applications. Furthermore, the component
should not be confused with the Information pop-up note even though the data
displayed in these two components can at times be identical.</p>
<table id="GUID-77983E22-5C85-4810-83B0-F52EFC18D428"><title>Default touch
events in Preview Pop-Up</title>
<tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.80*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.01*"/><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.19*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry valign="top"><p>User action</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>State change</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>Feedback</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down / release in Preview pop-up area</p></entry>
<entry><p>Application-specific</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Tactile feedback follows the component-specific functionality.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down / release outside Preview pop-up</p></entry>
<entry><p>Application-specific</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: No effect</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and hold</p></entry>
<entry><p>Application-specific</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic tactile feedback and audio feedback is provided with
touch down event.</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<note> No tactile feedback is provided with preview pop-up. Applications need
to take care of tactile feedback for the interactive elements inside Preview
pop-up.</note>
<p/>
<section id="GUID-0381A2A3-571D-4C1D-A418-AA0C71ECB681"><title>Preview pop-up
in a touch interface</title><p>Preview pop-up is not a touch-only component,
and its basic functionality is described above. Although it is
not recommended to place buttons or other items that appear touch-enabled
into the preview pop-up, it is still possible to give some items touch-only
functions. It is up to each application to decide whether to make use of this
support in some sensible way. For example, a tap on a www hyperlink displayed
in the preview pop-up would open Browser and open the Web site in question.
However, it should be noted that using touch-enabled items in the preview
pop-up is an advanced, heavy-user feature.</p><p>A tap on an item in the preview
pop-up can also open the stylus pop-up menu, when there is no obvious direct
function for that item. For more information, see <xref href="GUID-C4E728B4-3E84-49A4-83CB-DF146420D78A.dita">Stylus
pop-up menu</xref>.</p></section>
<section id="GUID-BE7B9950-53D3-4BB5-8971-4CBD0D57CE51"><title>Preview pop-up
for touch only</title><p>The above section describes the general case for
touch and the preview pop-up. There is, however, a variance possibility for
the preview pop-up, which is to limit it strictly for touch. In this case,
the guideline for having no buttons or other obvious touch items in the preview
pop-up can be ignored for the most part: if the preview pop-up can only be
opened with a stylus, it is perfectly acceptable to make touch functions plainly
touch-enabled.</p></section>
<section id="GUID-AC64544E-D3D9-451C-B0EF-FF3F54B280DF"><title>Using
preview pop-ups in applications</title><p>The API to use for creating the
preview pop-up component is the <xref format="html" href="specs/Guides/Information_Preview_Popup_API_Specification/Information_Preview_Popup_API_Specification.html" scope="peer">Information preview pop-up API</xref>.</p><p>Preview pop-ups
can be used in two modes: in the default mode where the pop-up is hidden automatically
as a result of time-out or input event (either a key press or a pointer event),
or in permanent mode where the pop-up stays visible until it is dismissed
by the application code. </p><p>For implementation information, see <xref format="html" href="specs/Guides/Information_Preview_Popup_API_Specification/Information_Preview_Popup_API_Specification.html#Information_Preview_Popup_API_Specification.topic3" scope="peer">Using the Information Preview Pop-up API</xref>. </p></section>
</conbody></concept>