<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-97C9A782-A7DE-480B-9DE0-97B213AAEDD0" xml:lang="en"><title>Query
input</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>Query input is a full screen component for displaying data query with direct
possibility for touch input. It uses the full screen. It is a standalone component
from input methods and thus user cannot change the input method from the Query
input. </p>
<p>In addition to data query content, it has Backspace button and ITU-T keypad
buttons. Softkeys are also displayed as buttons next to the editor, instead
of Control pane. This component is used for (PIN, PUK, time and date) queries
in start-up, and also in password editors. </p>
<p>Prompt text can be displayed in three lines, for example, “PIN code blocked”
and “Enter PIN code”, and is always aligned close to input field.</p>
<fig id="GUID-F92C4319-A768-41A0-99E8-07CA89C4BB08">
<title>Example of alpha-numeric input mode in portrait and landscape.</title>
<image href="GUID-B2523978-4262-4E32-B50D-4818AC561B6D_d0e63913_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>If only number entry is enabled, the Query input displays number buttons.</p>
<fig id="GUID-01C7366B-3342-4A0C-9112-16D32FECAE96">
<title>Example of numeric input mode in portrait and landscape.</title>
<image href="GUID-56E67157-08EE-414A-9EC5-ADAF27E0D36A_d0e63924_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig>
<p>In other data queries, the touch input is opened with touch down and release
to the editor. In query input, the input is instantly available for immediate
usage. Some buttons may be dimmed if needed. Both portrait and landscape orientations
are available for Query input. </p>
<p>Tactile feedback follows the virtual ITU-T feedback.</p>
<p>The following table lists the default touch events for query input:</p>
<table id="GUID-8281913F-8956-402B-B0F6-D3AD2347C83B"><title>The default touch
events for query input</title>
<tgroup cols="3">

<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.80*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.01*"/>
<colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.19*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry valign="top"><p>User action</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>State change</p></entry>
<entry valign="top"><p>Feedback</p></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release on left softkey.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Confirms the query. </p><p>It is initially dimmed and changed active
when first character is entered.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect and audio feedback are provided with
touch down and basic button effect with release events.</p></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><p>Touch down and release on right softkey.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Cancels the query.</p></entry>
<entry><p>Tactile: Basic button effect and audio feedback are provided with
touch down and basic button effect with release events.</p></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></conbody></concept>