<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-F23BB1F1-CF90-597F-8410-34AB8B567501" xml:lang="en"><title>PIM Subsystem
Overview</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<section id="GUID-201D8954-325A-422C-94D3-772274154AF9"><title>Purpose</title> <p>This
document describes storage, organisation and utility functionalities within
Symbian platform Personal Information Management (PIM) technology, as defined
by its subsystems: Application Engines and Application Services. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-78706FAF-6F53-4DFD-B77B-BA44C5E087B2"><title>Key Concepts</title> <p> <i>Application
Engines</i> - provide PIM data storage and manipulation. </p> <p> <i>Application
Services</i> - provide a collection of utility components.</p> <p> Application
Engines and Application Services enable user applications to acquire, organise,
maintain, and retrieve personal information. </p> <p> <i>Subsystem</i> - a
cohesive group of components within a single technology. </p> <p> <i>Component</i> -
the smallest unit of architectural significance and the finest grained unit
of description. </p> </section>
<section id="GUID-A76EE4BC-565F-4F5E-8943-1F9BE03B4D07"><title>Architectural
Relationships</title> <p>PIM <xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita">Application
Services</xref> technology delivers high-level OS services for storage and
manipulation of user data (such as a collection of Calendar and Contacts items).
PIM subsystem components are part of Application Engines and Application Services.
The Symbian platform Generic Middleware layer contains the following PIM components:
Alarm Server, Time Zone Server and Help Model. </p> <p>All the components
are contained between the OS Services layer and the User Interface layer. </p> <p>Key
clients of these components are licensee applications that use subsystems
such as Telephony, SyncML and Messaging. </p> <fig id="GUID-5335C9B9-5C4E-5673-AB93-59C921C3AC58">
<title>PIM Subsystem components are part of the Application Services and Generic
Middleware layers</title>
<image href="GUID-1742B2A1-6EC1-5368-919B-362516A5D452_d0e368182_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig> </section>
<section id="GUID-AEA465F8-77B5-45A6-B5A4-12083A9008F4"><title>Application
Engines</title> <p>Application Engines provide data storage and manipulation
for user data. </p><ul>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-A1227CAE-EE08-5EAF-8D15-81465467C0C0.dita#GUID-A1227CAE-EE08-5EAF-8D15-81465467C0C0/GUID-85D629ED-30D4-5608-A816-07BD375C6A76">Calendar</xref> enables
management of calendar entries and provides access to calendar stores. The
CalInterimAPI library is the Calendar data store. </p></li>
<li><p>The <xref href="GUID-A1227CAE-EE08-5EAF-8D15-81465467C0C0.dita#GUID-A1227CAE-EE08-5EAF-8D15-81465467C0C0/GUID-5F20F757-46F6-5652-AB0F-6B22DBB61111">Contacts
model</xref> provides a unified interface for managing contact information. </p></li>
</ul> </section>
<section id="GUID-D6AC13D1-3C9F-44B2-8691-3F4583E7D805"><title>Application
Services</title> <p>Application Services are used by multiple application
engines or applications running on Symbian. </p> <ul>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-8BD6CF61-80B6-5869-AB85-F572C590DB30">Alarm
Server</xref> maintains a queue of system-wide alarms. </p></li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-32519F1C-429A-59C9-B945-D0B1F81A0AA5">Calendar
Conversion</xref> converts dates between Gregorian and Chinese lunar calendar
dates for applications requiring Chinese date support. </p></li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-6EB921E1-0048-5388-8983-87172763FAB3">Help
model</xref> manages a collection of files that provide context-sensitive
help information. </p></li>
<li><p>Notepad API is a middleware tool that you can write simple text to
and save for future reference. </p>  </li>
<li><p>The Calendar Interim Utils2 is an Organizer API that provides methods
you can use to keep track of your time. It displays the individual days of
a given time period. You can add notes and memos to these dates to organize
your schedule.</p>  </li>
<li><p>Phonebook APIs provide methods useful in creating a contacts database
and performing various operations on it. These APIs expand on the Contact
model.</p>  </li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-4268D6AA-F468-5461-88A2-D6852D4AC69A">Time
zone localization</xref> provides localized versions of time zone and city
names. </p></li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-D30706E5-7191-5349-A883-C200B73AFED1">Time
zone server</xref> allows clients to obtain accurate conversion between any
time expressed in UTC and local time for a user's time zone. </p></li>
<li><p><xref href="GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48.dita#GUID-F43E458D-6650-5BB0-871D-2E4EB1353C48/GUID-9DFB0954-9CDF-5DAF-BA7A-54A1D64833F7">Versit</xref> is
a set of utility classes that support the import and export of data that is
formatted according to a set of standards initially defined by the Versit
consortium. </p></li>
</ul><p>There are no strong relationships between any of the subsystem components.
They are presented as a subsystem because they enable development of a set
of related applications.</p></section>
</conbody></concept>