<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-FE9017F4-4197-472F-A3E7-267169A51ABD" xml:lang="en"><title>Registration</title><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<p>You need to register your applications in order to make them visible
to the application menu and to provide other information to the underlying
operating system. To register, you need to provide a registration resource
file, typically named <parmname>&lt;application_name&gt;_reg.rss</parmname> that
contains the non-localized information for your application. Examples of non-localized
information include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>UID of the application</p></li>
<li><p>name of the application executable, without an extension</p>
</li>
<li><p>application properties, such as embeddability or whether
it is hidden</p></li>
</ul>
<p>For more information on how to create a registration file for the non-localized
information for your application, see <xref href="GUID-BF1AAA0D-DF2F-4E1D-A0D2-F419BD32F97A.dita">Creating
registration resource files</xref>. </p>
<p>You also need to provide localized information for your applications,
such as captions and icons. This is done by either including a name and path
of a localizable icon and caption resource file or the symbolic ID of a <parmname>LOCALISABLE_APP_INFO</parmname> data
structure in your application UI resource file. For a discussion of the available
options for where you can place this resource statement, see <xref href="jar:GUID-35228542-8C95-4849-A73F-2B4F082F0C44.jar!/sdk/doc_source/ToolsAndUtilities94/DevTools/RegFiles/Tool_Guide_LocalisableIconFile.html#Tool_Guide_LocalisableIconFile" format="application/java-archive">Localisable
icon/caption definition files</xref>. </p>
<p>You may define the following localized information:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>application caption, which is typically displayed next to
the icon in the application menu</p></li>
<li><p>short caption used by some mobile devices when screen space
is limited</p></li>
<li><p>name of the icon file</p></li>
</ul>
<p>For more information on using the <parmname>LOCALISABLE_APP_INFO</parmname> data
structure, see <xref href="GUID-9F90A2F0-9C76-4871-A766-D1AE0FC42C08.dita">Defining
localizable registration information</xref></p>
<note>
<p>You must compile both the non-localized information registration resource
file and the localized information resource file and include the results in
your package file in order for your application to be registered in a mobile
device.</p>

</note>
</conbody></concept>