<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 2007-2010 Nokia Corporation and/or its subsidiary(-ies) All rights reserved. -->
<!-- This component and the accompanying materials are made available under the terms of the License 
"Eclipse Public License v1.0" which accompanies this distribution, 
and is available at the URL "http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html". -->
<!-- Initial Contributors:
    Nokia Corporation - initial contribution.
Contributors: 
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="GUID-BE2D9AAB-203B-471A-984D-91E917611641" xml:lang="en"><title>Application
Level Roaming</title><shortdesc>Application-level roaming (ALR) enables your application to roam
to use the best available data connection while operational.</shortdesc><prolog><metadata><keywords/></metadata></prolog><conbody>
<section id="GUID-F6E3E184-0235-47B1-950F-AECA2F64D985"><title>Implementation
Considerations</title>      <p>There is no SDK method for WLAN scanning. Your
application should use Connection Monitor Server API to request the list of
available access points or network names (in the case of a WLAN these are
SSIDs). Connection Monitor Server API also provides notifications about changes
in the access point availability list. </p><p>Handovers between GPRS and WCDMA
radio networks take a long time (from 15 seconds to 2 minutes) and sometimes
fail completely. You should use long application level timers (if any) and
maintain a responsive UI. Note that handovers between GPRS and WCDMA cannot
be controlled by the symbian platform (except with fixed settings). The control
logic is in the cellular modem. </p><p> In ALR, the transfer from one connection
to another always introduces an IP address change and a break in data connection
(even with make-before-break when the break is really short). This is because
the sockets need to be closed and re-opened. This may be problematic for the
applications that maintain a stateful connection with a server in the network.
The workaround for a break is to open a new RConnection handle when receiving <xref href="GUID-4D26288F-A8F8-355E-B49C-B313EEC04584.dita"><apiname>PreferredCarrierAvailable()</apiname></xref> and
establishing the server connection using that (if the application protocol
allows such operation). When that is done and new sockets are created for
the new RConnection, the original RConnection can be closed. There is no workaround
for the IP address change.</p>     </section>
<section id="GUID-011DBF55-366F-4AC7-824A-2B485658E1C8"><title>Process Flow</title><fig id="GUID-79B01634-BBA5-40DD-BBB5-DE4D53139BC6">
<title>Application-level roaming</title>
<image href="GUID-8305F179-8F26-4B38-8523-066D1B0B7A62_d0e217254_href.png" placement="inline"/>
</fig></section>
<section id="GUID-A2C485F5-0BD5-4D0E-8F95-D9963C4C819F"><title>Additional
information</title><p>The following APIs are used to implement application-level
roaming: </p><ol>
<li id="GUID-B1B6B16A-A790-4B04-BC6E-91D64E5C4E06"><p> Sockets Server Client
API (ESOCK) is the API for all IP-based socket communication. It remains unchanged,
but applications need to be ready to close and open sockets at certain times
to roam for a better connection.</p></li>
<li id="GUID-F4D709CC-9F14-42B4-BF32-8EB0C787EBF3"><p>Connection Management
API (RConnection) is a collection of Symbian's connection management-related
functionalities provided by ESOCK. It contains several extensions and one
of them is the mobility extension. The term "mobility API" actually refers
to the mobility extensions that are part of Connection Manager API and defined
in header <filepath>cs_mobility_apiext.h</filepath>. With the so-called mobility
API the client application can register for mobility events, receive information
about preferred connections, indicate whether to switch to a new connection
or ignore it. In short, it enables ALR for the applications.</p></li>
</ol><p> The mobility extension functionality of the Connection
Manager API is provided by classes<xref href="GUID-9A3979A9-F882-3053-B5B1-E0E125774271.dita"><apiname> MMobilityProtocolResp </apiname></xref>and <xref href="GUID-6CA83252-4D0C-3B72-83ED-B5152B666C83.dita"><apiname>CActiveCommsMobilityApiExt</apiname></xref>. </p><p>Methods
that must be implemented by client (class MMobilityProtocolResp): <ol>
<li id="GUID-F6747252-65DF-4424-BA7E-DA5D11D2E9BE"><p><b>virtual void PreferredCarrierAvailable(TAccessPointInfo
aOldAP, TAccessPointInfo aNewAP, TBool aIsUpgrade, TBool aIsSeamless )</b>;
This method is called by the middleware to notify a client about a new preferred
connection.</p></li>
<li id="GUID-9C0DD06E-9949-4A7B-ABF9-CEF10F541274"><p><b>virtual void NewCarrierActive(TAccessPointInfo
aNewAP, TBool aIsSeamless );</b> This method is called by the middleware to
notify a client that a preferred connection has been activated.</p></li>
<li id="GUID-54247E78-0A68-4A2A-B94A-064BE9D61270"><p><b>virtual void Error(TInt
aError);</b> This method is called by middleware to notify that there are
no suitable connections available.</p></li>
</ol></p><p>Methods provided by ESock (class CActiveCommsMobilityApiExt): <ol>
<li id="GUID-CFEC6776-0206-4205-9269-7AD2A47CDF23"><p><b>void MigrateToPreferredCarrier();</b> Client
can indicate that it wants to start using a new preferred connection as a
response to PreferredCarrierAvailable().</p></li>
<li id="GUID-D5181565-96D3-4025-8A7E-B92EE4C699ED"><p><b>void IgnorePreferredCarrier();</b> Client
can indicate that it doesn’t want to use a new preferred connection as a response
to PreferredCarrierAvailable().</p></li>
<li id="GUID-4C9658D0-D0F3-40A6-9466-D2CBB15D2663"><p><b>void NewCarrierAccepted();</b> Client
indicates that a new connection is working for it.</p></li>
<li id="GUID-33856021-74DA-4501-9DCB-8B28BD281282"><p><b>void NewCarrierRejected();</b> Client
indicates that a new connection is not working and it wants to use another
connection. In this case it receives <xref href="GUID-4D26288F-A8F8-355E-B49C-B313EEC04584.dita"><apiname>PreferredCarrierAvailable()</apiname></xref> again
with probably the original connection as a preferred one. The non-working
access point is blacklisted for that client and not suggested again.</p></li>
</ol></p></section>
</conbody></concept>